this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software for software engineering radio
this is Robert bloomin I have with me
today Brent Laster his day job is a
senior manager in R&D at sass Brent is
also the author of two books
professional git and Jenkins two up and
running I'm gonna read the subtitle of
that book evolve your deployment
pipeline for next generation automation
he frequently presents trainings for
O'Reilly Safari on git Jenkins
deployment pipelines and continuous
delivery he's also a regular presenter
at OSCON
devops world Jenkins world rich web
experience and other conferences Brent
welcome to software engineering radio
thanks Robert I appreciate the
invitation to appear on the show would
you like to add anything else about your
bio that I didn't cover I think that
covers it pretty well okay today we're
gonna be talking about Jenkins - subject
of your book and we will link to that
book in the show notes Jenkins is a
build server we're gonna work up to a
discussion about Jenkins but I want to
get some background concepts in could
you give us a brief review of see ICD
we've covered that on a couple of shows
two twenty one and two eleven so
listeners can go back and listen to
those but let's get a quick summary of
that sure you know I tend to think of CI
and see these continuous ideas
continuous integration continuous
delivery as being kind of like an
assembly line and continuous integration
is the process that kind of kicks off
the assembly line it's the updating
source code out in a source management
system and having some process like
Jenkins that monitors those
posit or ease and then kicks off the
rest of the pipeline from there that
goes into what's really called
continuous delivery is a larger set of
getting your code from source management
through testing building all the pieces
of the pipeline and kind of putting it
through more and more what we call
continuous testing more and more broader
sets of tests there to prove that it is
of a high quality that it works well
with other pieces of code other things
that have been built through the
pipeline and down into you get to
continuous deployment the idea that you
have produced something that is of a
high enough quality and works well
enough that it could be deployed doesn't
mean you deploy it every time but you
have proven that it can be deployed so
it goes to the assembly line and you get
something out the other side from your
source code change that you would feel
comfortable deploying to customers if
you chose to do so could you clarify
what is continuous about it as compared
to plain old integration and deployment
well so could continuous is is kind of a
perhaps an overused terms in a lot of
cases but it continuous implies
typically a couple of things it implies
that it's a repeatable process it's more
of a discipline or science than an art
it's not somebody handcrafting processes
together it's something that can be
reproduced you've given the same inputs
you get the same outputs out there also
it is expected to be fairly fast there's
an idea of fail fast in the process if
something is not going to work you want
to find that out quickly but you also
want to be able to produce something
that is deployable or eligible to be
deployed in a fairly quick manner so
some companies will do it as often as
you know multiple times a day some
companies will choose to do it once a
day it depends on their but it is more
of a repeatable fast process to get the
source code changes through there in
your description you used a couple of
terms pipeline and assembly line drill
down into what you mean
by pipeline so pipeline can have a lot
of meanings but typically the way I
think of it is the set of processes that
are changed together the set of
processes for what it would take to take
your change from source code again to a
deliverable product out there those can
include processes for compiling and
building the code doing unit tests
functional tests integration tests
gathering source code metrics putting
them into repositories with other
artifacts combining them getting them
ready for deployment putting them into
containers all those kinds of things so
a pipeline in simplest terms would just
be a chain of processes linked together
those are things you need to do every
one of those things for a change to be
production ready in most cases yes
although pipelines actually may have
some points of human interaction in them
for example a user acceptance test might
be part of the pipeline where a user
wants to go in and try some stuff out
make sure that stuff looks in the user
interface so there are typically pieces
of the pipeline they all run automated
but there may be points along the way
where it's incumbent upon a human or
where it's desire to have a human say
yes I want to go ahead and proceed to
the next stage we're gonna now move on
more specifically to the Jenkins piece
Jenkins is a build server what is a
build server well in its it's primarily
been used for builds but it's really an
automation tool it's a workflow
Orchestrator and that's a perhaps a
fancy way of saying that it can automate
processes and connect them together and
monitor them so that's where it really
comes into its power there as being able
to model processes to find them and Link
jobs together in code now right out
there pipeline is code in there and be
able to monitor and report problems and
execute it be able to run this kind of
pipeline now that can be a lot more than
builds it can be all the piece
of the pipeline the testing the running
other applications for example to gather
metrics and to do all the different
pieces I think I've billed as compiling
or maybe merging a large number of files
into some kind of an archive you saying
that's really something we started out
with but the term it's much more generic
now and can apply to almost any step
that you need to do to get your code
ready for delivery right that the
gentleman who created of Jenkins which
was originally called Hudson Kazuki
Kawaguchi and I'm probably saying his
name wrong and I apologize for that but
he said he got tired of being the guy
who broke the bill so that was why he
originally created Jenkins the idea
originally was as more of a CI that
continuous integration monitoring for
changes coming into the source
management system and in kicking off
builds but then as continuous delivery
this idea of continuous delivery has
evolved has grown in popularity Jenkins
was a logical tool to take that and to
implement the other pieces of the
pipeline downstream so today we can
really use Jenkins and the functionality
provides to drive any other number of
applications and different pieces or
processes to make up an entire pipeline
you may have answered this already I'm
gonna ask and see if I get something
else back from you what is the role of
the build server within the CI CD
process so depends on what you kind of
mean by the build server today we
typically would talk more about like a
build application that is probably run
by something like Jenkins these days it
might be something like Gradle or in the
past maven or any number of compilers or
applications that actually build the
code the build server typically or the
build system is typically where the
process takes off and starts after you
have code pushed into source control and
something like Jenkins has detected it
and kicked off the builds the build is
the first point
of identifying a problem or failure in
there to make sure things look good
these days they typically will also
encompass unit testing and their
individual tests to be able to make sure
that code changes work kind of an
isolation giving the same thing some
inputs for a function you get the
expected outputs and that so the build
is the first place in there where you
want to validate that your code looks
good
typically though that's in an isolated
in isolation and then you move it on
down the pipeline to test it out with
the other pieces
let's move more specifically into
Jenkins we've been talking about general
concepts that could apply regardless of
the tool situate Jenkins in the
landscape of comparable tools what what
does it do what is it good at so that's
a good question
so Jenkins as I've said it's kind of an
orchestration engine that's probably a
workflow tool that's probably the best
way to think about it
it allows you to tie other tools
together into this sort of pipelines
that you need to do or do monitoring on
other things out there with the jenkins
to release which is what we kind of used
to call the jenkins 2.0 and beyond it's
changed in the from the interface the
interface used to be more of a what was
called free style you would interact
with the web forms and you would select
stuff and drop-down list you would type
stuff in fields with Jenkins - now you
can essentially write these pipeline
beasts as this orchestration processes
just as you would a program you can
write it in code out there and you can
store it even with your source code in
the repository and Jenkins can monitor
that code as a change so this really
ties into the whole DevOps idea here of
being able that your infrastructure your
processes can be expressed as code as
well and be monitored and pick up and
cause a new run of things when something
changes out there that's a really
important point I want to drill down
more into that I've been doing some work
in the last couple of weeks with Jenkins
one every other server or we manage in
my DevOps group the configuration
management tool will generate a conf if
you have an ABC server it would generate
abc.com using templating it can function
as a programming language do anything
you want to get the right conf drop it
on the server and then tell the server
hey reload conf
Jenkins 1 the server can modify the
configuration file and it's not under
source control so it's not DevOps
friendly so it sounds like Jenkins 2 the
goal was to make it more compatible with
how DevOps works in modern environments
absolutely we as you said in the earlier
versions of Jenkins typically your
configuration was stored in XML files
out there and the Jenkins home directory
and you had to back that up or use a
plug-in or something to keep track of
changes to it and with Jenkins 2 they
have really made writing your pipeline
as code as we call it being able to
express your your infrastructure by were
coding it up in a Jenkins application
and storing it with the source control
they've really made that a first-class
construct out there it's it's prime when
the primary focus is of Jenkins 2 and
again it really does tie in nicely to
the ho DevOps infrastructure there
because not only can I code up my
pipeline in the Jenkins application
itself and test it that way and evaluate
it and make sure it all works
I can also store it as what's called a
jenkins file an external file that has
that code in it put it in source control
point jenkins at that and say watch this
just as you would for source control for
a continuous integration watch this file
and if something changes in that file go
out and create a job to automatically
run my pipeline based on what's in that
file so it really does carry Jenkins to
where it needs to be in terms of really
integrating well with the DevOps ideals
you mentioned the jenkins file talked
about what goes into the jenkins file so
jenkins file is is
basically the storing the code that you
type into Jenkins that you would enter
in Jenkins or you can do it directly
into Jenkins file but it's storing the
code that describes your pipeline yeah
as in a external file it's like a if you
think about like a build script or
something that has a certain expected
name maybe like the Gradle build file
that sort of thing a Jenkins file is the
Jenkins piece of that it's the named
Jenkins file it's just a text file with
the program code to run your pipeline
out there they do have a couple of
different formats you can express your
pipeline in one called scripted syntax
and one called declarative syntax
scripted syntax gets you it's basically
Jenkins steps DSL steps DSL being
domain-specific language that are
supplied by plugins out there any plugin
you put in Jenkins can supply steps that
you can use in your script so a scripted
pipeline is those steps and groovy code
of groovy programming language you can
use that in there the declarative syntax
is an alternative way to write your
pipeline it's again makes the steps
available but it's more about declaring
what you need instead of doing the kind
of imperative coding just saying I need
these tools I need these applications
those kinds of things
and letting Jenkins figure out how to
how to do it they're both pipeline as
code just altering its syntax and some
are easier for some people to deal with
than the others we did a show a while
back on declarative programming in
DevOps
many DevOps tools are declarative what
is your view on the pros and cons versus
the scripted jenkins file versus
declarative jenkins file and and which
one would you adopt if you were starting
a new project so that's that's a good
question and I did a lot of
consideration looking at this when I was
writing the book and talking with people
there and everybody of course has
different opinions about it so it
originally started with the scripted
pipeline scripted syntax you have more
flexibility and more freedom to do the
kinds of things you would normally do if
your
grammar out there in terms of adding in
loops into your code or using any valid
groovy syntax to finding variables even
those kinds of things in there so if
you're a programmer by nature or you
want to have the flexibility to use kind
of chronic constructs like loops or
variables and those kinds of things
the inscripted syntax is the way to go
the declarative syntax came about
because the cloudBees the ones who
contribute and the jenkins community
wanted to have make it easier for people
who were coming from the original
jenkins in the original jenkins
prior to 2.0 versions out there as I
said you normally filled in web forms
you had fields that you would fill in or
drop-down lists and stuff so it was very
much about a very structured process
there are two defining the jobs and
declarative feels more like that it's a
very well structure you have a very
well-defined structure out there to use
that to fill in information about what
you need so if you are not a programmer
for example and coming just from using
Jenkins before declarative may feel more
comfortable to you you have to realize
though that declarative is a bit in my
opinion more limited in terms of having
less flexibility and stuff because not
everything can be done with all plugins
necessarily without like defining
variables and stuff in there the other
thing about declarative though is it is
much better because there's a structured
about checking for syntax errors and
identifying where problems occur in your
code because it can monitor the
structure of that it also is a better
fit for their new GUI interface out
there blue ocean because declarative is
very structured and structural objects
can map better into a visual interface
out there
you mentioned the ability of plug-ins to
supply different keywords or tasks that
are used in the Jenkins file given
examples what are some of the more
useful or popular plugins well certainly
of course you have source management
plugins out there like git which supply
a git step that you can put into your
program to say you get and you can
supply a branch or a location for the
repository out there probably one of the
there are some that come with the code
like this shell step the SH step to run
code out there on a UNIX shell or the
bat step to run stuff on a Windows thing
out there
but any plug-in that you installed that
is compatible with Jenkins 2 is expected
to supply a step that can be used in the
pipeline code now
so any of the ones I've used like sonar
cube for code analysis or artifactory
different ones they will all supply
steps that you can use and hook into
there so if there's there's a wealth of
plugins and in fact that's probably why
the Jenkins is as popular as it is it's
just because of the huge number of
plugins that are available for it and
now they all should supply steps that
you can use in your code does Jenkins
provide a plug-in provider interface so
that anyone in the community can create
a plug-in and it should work I'm sure
there is that there are examples out
there of how to create plugins and how
to work with them these days the plugins
again are expected to provide those
kinds of steps they're also expected to
be re-entrant meaning that if the master
server the master node goes down that
they can survive or restart so you have
to make sure you can that plugins can
serialize their data they can write
their data to disk and pick up again if
the master or stops from that so but
within those kinds of boundaries
certainly you can write plugins out
there Jenkins also supports a feature
called global variables which is kind of
like defining an object in methods
associated with it that you can add in
as well you can use shared pipeline
libraries and bring things in well so
lots of so certainly lots of
opportunities for people to develop new
code and new functionality and
contribute back you mentioned this idea
of plugins being re-entrant we did an
earlier show on workflow management
systems as you point out a few minutes
ago
Incans is a workflow engine one of the
characteristics is these jobs which you
call pipelines and multiple steps you
could have different failure modes that
could occur between steps is Jenkins
able to reliably complete a pipeline in
spite of different kinds of failures
that might occur or system restarts
things like that
the idea with the with Jenkins 2 again
is that the system is supposed to be
re-entrant or that job should be
reentrant and that's dependent upon the
the plugins ability again to serialize
their data out to disk and be able to
pick up at the end if something happens
on the master side so to that degree yes
it is re-entrant in there now when you
are when you move from like coding and
web forms to actually writing your code
as as writing your pipeline is code out
there especially like in the scripted
syntax there's more responsibility on
you to be able to handle exception cases
so just like in any programming
environment like Java groovy those sorts
of things if you're using scripted
pipeline syntax you would typically use
like try-catch functionality to be able
to catch exceptions and then handle
those well if you kind of have to do
that and the scripted pipeline to get
that post to build functionality that
you used to get for free in traditional
Jenkins the thing that says no matter if
my pipeline succeeds or fails I'll still
send email to notify people so you have
to kind of work around that a little bit
of these kind of programming constructs
and scripted syntax in declarative
syntax they've done more for this and
there actually is a post section
directive there that you can include in
your code and just put that in there and
that will always get executed at the end
so it's both a combination of what the
plugins provide in terms of being
re-entrant and being able to pick up
again but also there's some
responsibilities on you as the coder of
the pipeline to use the appropriate
method to make sure that you can survive
those kinds of cases as well what's an
example of an exception in a
build step that you would want to catch
rather than allow the job to fill well
for example if something happened in in
general of his and a job there are
various constructs in Jenkins for flow
control such as retry in there that will
retry an operation for a certain number
of times and if it goes past that time I
still can't do it it throws an exception
that's the way that it indicated that it
needed that it couldn't complete it and
so you would need to catch that
exception then to keep your program from
aborting if you're using scripted syntax
there and be able to handle it
gracefully and continue on what about if
we have a step that is compiling a
program and compilation fails due to an
error syntax error in the program that
seems to me that's a pretty normal thing
and you'd want to handle that rather
than the entire pipeline going into a
failed state well it if you have a
syntax error though chances are you want
to detect that and alert the the person
who did it or somehow alert people to
that first because the pipeline doesn't
can't proceed down the firown' test down
the further steps of testing code and
doing all the other steps if the code
doesn't compile in the first place you
know certainly you could catch that
workaround that sort of thing in there
too but more normally you probably would
want to at least flag that and at least
notify people about it so they could
deal with it quickly in that case this
would be a common thing not only
completions fail but other types of
conditions where you want to notify what
is are there plugins that Jenkins uses
to communicate with the development team
through different slack email yeah
absolutely in fact there's a there's a
chapter in the book that I wrote just on
about notifications in there and
reporting and we have examples and there
of using things like slack out there and
other social media things to communicate
status back
a for any kind of application that you
can think of pretty much these days that
used in software development producing
software there's usually a plugin for
Jenkins and the social media things are
no exception out there so certainly you
can have notifications back to select
teams you can have colors in there you
can define all kinds of criteria there
of course the most common one is it were
arguably I guess the most common one
still is the email notifications you
certainly can send out email
notifications and there are all kinds of
advanced setups for those kinds of
things so again using plugins you just
have to find the plug-in that you need
and you can pretty much tie into any of
those applications I want to move on now
talk more about scaling and distributing
Jenkins I can download install run on a
single server
how many Jenkins jobs are what can I
support on one server you know I don't
actually know what the limits are out
there I would say it's probably
dependent I know upon your
infrastructure and there too but
certainly I know we have I've seen a ton
that's over not an exact number of
course a ton of stuff things out there
and I think it just depends on the
infrastructure out there of course you
want to set up you know you can set up
different nodes and one of the things
you think about with Jenkins is having
the master the master is not really
intended to do a lot of heavy lifting
it's more about managing the processes
managing these jobs and having access to
things but it really has what they call
a lightweight executor so typically
you're trying to farm stuff off to nodes
out there and you can define nodes for
example that you know you might have a
group of nodes that has a label as I
call it an identifier that says these
are our Windows nodes or these are our
UNIX nodes over here or maybe these are
on the east coast or west coast out
there and so then you can in your
pipeline select the particular node you
want to send stuff to and that's a big
advantage as well and the other thing
I'll say about Jenkins to stuff they've
done a lot of integration for containers
in particular
were things like docker so you can have
a docker file the thing describes how to
build a container and give that to
Jenkins and it can spin up an agent or a
virtual node based off of that so
there's a lot of capabilities within
your pipeline code to fire up containers
and run processes on that which gives
you a lot of flexibility than
distributing workloads that way I think
you are you have been talking about
Jenkins as a distributed system could
you give overview what is the
architecture of the distributed system
we're talking about nodes so we have the
server which is the master and then a
fleet of nodes right so there's a couple
of terms that that are used in Jenkins
the master system and then they will
talk about if you're working with
declarative pipelines to talk about
agents if we're working with scripted
pipelines you're talking they talk about
nodes out there for all intents and
purposes you can think of nodes and
agents and stuff at the same time but
again the idea is that I have a master
Jenkins system but I farm the work out
the various jobs whether it's a
traditional Jenkins job or a pipeline
job as we're talking about now whatever
out to these nodes or agents out there
and an agent or can be anything from a
docker container to an actual you know
bare metal kind of system out there
whatever makes sense it could be
something across the country it could be
whatever out there so the real
distributed power of Jenkins comes in
being able to farm these jobs out and
send them to the most appropriate system
to run them on and it's very easy with
in Jenkins because of this idea of a
label a label is just an identifier that
you can attach to any of these nodes and
you could have the same label on
multiple nodes so like I said if you had
ones that run Windows you might have a
farm of systems all labeled as Windows
that you could just say send this thing
to the Windows node and it
send it automatically out there and then
the results run and the results come
back to the master so you can see the
output there but that sort of a
structure makes it actually very easy to
be able to send work out and distribute
the load if we have a number of Windows
nodes Jenkins needs to send a job is it
gonna pick one that presently is not too
heavily loaded and send a new work there
yeah it'll pick one that's available I
honestly don't know exactly what the
algorithm is in terms of whether it's
looking at the loads and stuff I'm sure
there are probably ways you can tune
that but I'm not sure how it's
implemented any underlying setup are you
aware if it has integration with cloud
provider services like Auto scale groups
where it can spin up a new capacity in
line with the workload and tear it down
as the workload declines I'm not
familiar with that I don't know exactly
what it can do with that but it might it
might have a chance to do that
what is a typical number of nodes or
agents that a master would have or not a
typical number but what's the range of
sizes you've seen in deployed
deployment well certainly I know where I
work we have quite a few systems out
there you know probably on the order
maybe of a hundred or so masters and
stuff and then nodes off of that you
know it really varies and I don't know I
don't know the best way to answer that I
think it varies from situation to
situation out there you know anywhere
from a single node to I'm sure there are
once I have probably 100 or so if
they're sitting out lots of stuff the
other factor that plays into this and
one that is more common I think these
days is the sort of ephemeral nodes the
idea of they call it the cloud there's
cloud plug-in for Jenkins where you can
spin up a docker container to run stuff
on on-demand and then when the job
finishes that goes away or you can spin
something up in AWS out there to run a
Jenkins job and when you're done it can
go away so it's not even necessarily
anymore having a constant number of
nodes always available it can be more of
the on-demand I spin up something with
docker or kubernetes or some of those
things to run the jobs when I need it
and then when I'm done it spins it down
I think takes it away you just answered
my earlier question about Auto scale
groups what I was really getting out was
ability to have job execution resources
on demand rather than have a fixed
number of nodes that may be idle half
the time sure sure yeah and that's one
of the nice things I've got a section in
the book about working with containers
and there that's one of the things we
talked about it's very simple and
Jenkins you can have things like the
cloud provider plug-in that goes out and
spin these up or you can even in your
pipeline code just say hey go
going to spin up a Jenkins Gandhara I'm
sorry docker container for this run my
code in it and then bring it back down
in fact there is a they call it a global
variable it's kind of like a step in the
code but there's a docker global
variable there's an inside method you
can call in your pipeline code that will
get an image down for you automatically
started up map your workspace in Jenkins
as a volume in the docker container then
within the inside method it's a has a
beginning and an end to it it has kind
of a block in there within that scope
you can call the shell steps SH steps
and any steps that you run in that block
will automatically be executed on the
docker container instead of on the the
Jenkins system itself so and then when
you're done this step will spin down to
the container and just make a little
record that says it was used in there so
just by calling one method on this
docker global variable you get all of
that functionality for free in there the
cloud providers mostly have different
ways of offering a docker container
execution as a service if you're able to
integrate with that then you don't need
to host your own execution
infrastructure at all right right I want
to move on now and talk about how jobs
are initiated what are the different
ways that a a job or a pipeline could
get started well typically if you're
starting with the continuous integration
sort of functionality there at the front
of the pipeline you're doing in a couple
ways for example you might be doing what
we call polling polling this the source
management system which says every
minute every five minutes however often
it is I go out and check and ask the
source management system do you have
anything new for me out there another
one in terms of that could just be that
periodically regardless of whether or
not there's something new out there you
can just go out and say I'm going to
build every hour every 15 minutes
however that is there's a
syntax out there it harkens back if you
know the old cron syntax out there to be
able to specify the day that the hour of
the week that sort of thing being able
to specify that for either polling or
for just periodically building out there
a couple of other ways you can do it
there is a tool called Garrett which is
designed to do kind of code reviews but
you can also have a kickoff builds it
basically works with git and kind of
catches your code before it gets all the
way and to get and says let me do things
like code reviews and verify changes and
it can communicate with Jenkins and kick
off test builds from that and then
finally there is an approach called like
a web hooks out there if you have code
on github for example you can define a
github webhook which will send a
notification they call it a payload over
to your Jenkins system when something
occurs on github if somebody makes a
change or updates a file whatever the
case may be
it will actually do kind of a push
notification send it across the way to
your Jenkins system of course for that
one that implies your Jenkins system has
to be accessible has to have a port open
that it github can communicate to but so
there's there's a couple of different
ways out there to kick off the builds
it's something I want to drill down into
a bit more typically developers changing
systems will create a branch and get did
I understand that we could have Jenkins
do run let's say a number of tests
manual steps like a code review on the
branch before it gets merged so I don't
want to deploy it but I do want to have
different kinds of tests passing before
I consider it ready to merge so that's
more of a function of the pipeline out
there I was referencing an application
called Garrett which is a separate
application that you can install and
your and have in your pipeline that
allows you to do the code reviews and
also integrates with Jenkins do pre
builds out there
and you can integrate you can use that
as one of the applications with the
Jenkins pipeline out there you there are
also other applications I mean github
has code review stuff in there and get
lab those things a lot of tools have
code review and those sorts of things
built into it but certainly once you get
your code into the source management
system as well so these those kinds of
applications let you look at the code
before it gets into the source
management system all the way once it
gets into the source management system
and the pipeline pulls the code out then
part of the typical continuous delivery
pipeline is running the integration
testing the functional testing and all
those successive levels of testing out
there to be able to prove the quality of
the code and to prove that it works in
there so you've got kind of bow before
the pipeline and kind of as it's in the
pipeline covering that if I understand
this I might define a Jenkins pipeline
let's say I call it developer pre-commit
and that pipeline consists of compile
the code run some integration tests
maybe run some unit tests produce a
report but that pipeline would not
include a deployment step and it's up to
me to use Gerrit or some other tool to
say when I want to run that Jenkins
pipeline and then I would wire that
pipeline up to run on branches when the
developer is ready to merge is that it
more or less kind of essentially if you
had like Gerrit out there garrett has a
plugin that integrates with jenkins and
so it would be you would probably define
a Jenkins job that would say when I put
code into Gerrit before it gets all the
way into into the git remote repository
I do a we might call like a review job
or a small review task in Jenkins and it
met only may just say when something
gets into Gerrit let me try and build it
and report back on it there and then
once you go ahead and get that
successful you could go ahead and say
merge this in the codes pass the basic
sanity check out there the review build
we had emergent in and then you could
have your other pipelines you're talking
about kicked off from based on that code
being merged in finally and then that
would kick off the rest of the
downstream processes I want to talk
about some security aspects many of
these things that Jenkins needs to do
like pulling docker images from a
registry interacting with cloud
providers are gonna require credentials
how does Jenkins manage the credentials
it needs so Jenkins has a whole lack of
a better word ecosystem around
credentials and it built-in credential
can define credential providers you can
define credential stores you can define
all kinds of credentials in there of
course SSH key certificates password
username passwords those kinds of things
so there is a whole credentials system
built into Jenkins in fact I devoted a
whole chapter in the book to around the
security aspects and credentials in
there so the basic idea is you define
the credentials that you want to use in
Jenkins and then within your pipeline
you have steps available that can use
those credentials and it's kind of kind
of cool of what they typically do is
they'll say there's a step say you know
with some credential you can define that
step and what it does is it takes the
credentials you've identified in Jenkins
takes the values and puts them into
environment variables so you can give an
environment variables names and then you
can use those environment variables in
the rest of your code without having to
expose those things so you're telling
Jenkins go out and grab those values out
of the credentials put them into these
variables here I'll use the variable
names in my code and so you can
reference those without ever having them
exposed out there or in case of like SSH
keys you can just say with SSH key and
you have a block of code and as long as
you're doing something within that block
it has access to those credentials we
did a show on hash C Corp vault and I'm
aware that cloud providers have some
similar
services are you saying then that
Jenkins has integration with services
like this it can communicate and say I
need the certificate to get this
resource from this other place give it
to me now
yeah it's Jenkins have again you can
define you define the credentials up
front that you want and then it's very
easy to access them in there as well and
I actually did a little section in the
book and the credentials thing where I
talked about some very simple
integration with fault has probably
gotten more sophisticated now but did
talk about some of using some of the
vault driving some of the vault stuff
from there so certainly again as these
new products come out and new features
come out there's more and more plugins
to integrate with them but the
credential system is a works pretty well
in Jenkins if you are running your own
nodes as servers the master has to get
access to them maybe SSH or how does the
master authenticate itself to do work on
one of the nodes or agents so there's a
couple of different ways most commonly
it's probably done via like SSH having
SSH keys there between the master and
the node out there there are some other
ways of some of the more traditional
like jnlp stuff you can startup nodes
that way you can authenticate various
ways the most common way though I've
seen it done is like through the driving
the SSH keys out there does Jenkins
implement users and is there
permissioning system for users
absolutely uh you Jenkins by default
which Incas - oh now it is secured from
the start so you go through the
installation process and it generates a
random password and you put the password
you have to go and find that password
and put it in to finish installing it to
set up the initial user but there is a
whole system around user and user
permissions again it's covered in that
section on security there you can define
various sort of security models there's
a role based access
plug in you can get to define it based
on roles out there there's also the
Jenkins typical kind of matrix setup
where you can define users and you can
use the matrix rows and columns
permissions to check off what
permissions people have and stuff in
there and it's actually kind of cool
since we're on the topic about users and
security here one of the things that
they've done in Jenkins too is if you
think about it when you are writing a
script you're writing a pipeline script
you can call any kind of methods you
want you can code any kind of thing you
want to in your script doesn't
necessarily mean you should be allowed
to do that so one of the features they
have is a called in script or process
approval out there basically if you're
an administrator you can run any kind of
script you want they assume you know
what you're doing if you're not an
administrator then what Jenkins will do
is it will the people can look if you're
using a thing called the sandbox and say
what methods are you calling in your
pipeline code and are those methods
allowed it has a whitelist that it keeps
to say is this method okay to be able to
be used out there if it's not if it's
not one of the allowed methods then it
will actually create a queue of and send
something to an administrator it says
you can't run your script until an
administrator looks at this and approves
it and it has a little in process script
approval out there where an
administrator can log in and say okay
this script is OK or this method call is
OK or it's not ok or it's ok if the user
has permission to run it so that's you
know they thought ahead to that at least
so it's not just like you can code up
anything and run it you it's actually
tied in to the permission system and
into the good list make sure that it's
OK to do we were talking a little while
back about you could have github when a
new commit comes in it could launch a
job through a web hook to test the code
in that commit this github does the
github webhook authenticate as a
specific user
as permission to execute that job I'd
have to go back and look at exactly what
it it doesn't there but I certainly
think that you have to have
authentication set up for the web book I
don't remember exactly how that works
through the process there let's move on
now and talk about deployment I'm
roughly gonna define that as moving your
code to run on a staging or production
network and that might involve
restarting parts of the system is that
something I would use Jenkins for well
typically I think of you know deployment
it deployment gave me so many things
these days as you said it kind of
roughly admits putting it out there so
it's available to you but it could mean
it's deploying it out to a cloud system
it could mean that it's making it
available on a website it's just putting
a you know a set of executables out
somewhere for it so depending on the
application and if you have a plugin and
stuff certainly you could drive that
through Jenkins if you have a process
that can be automated to deploy your
stuff out there there is no reason why
you couldn't use Jenkins to do that the
deployment then it might be a shell
script or there are tools like
Capistrano that give you the ability to
define scripts that will move your code
Jenkins doesn't necessarily know it's
doing deployment it's doing a job and
you define that job to do deployment
steps as you see it right Eddie there
are plugins I think look for Capistrano
and different things and even if it's
just deploying it into you know a Tomcat
system or something like that it's
fairly easy to have Jenkins be able to
do that any kind of command that you can
use to execute that should be able to be
done by Jenkins out there a lot of times
these days - it might even be deploying
it into a container creating a container
and putting it out there I've had jobs
that I've created that spin up docker
containers or create a war file take the
war file put it into Tomcat build a
docker image off of that and a docker
container and Link containers together
so really anything that you can draw
particularly the some kind of a
command-line interface or a plug-in
interface and like that can be used we
have a show coming up more specifically
about deployment it's an interesting
process it you can have a lot of failure
modes and you have to decide or maybe
set a policy that you roll back or you
roll forward is that something you'd
want to delegate to Jenkins I guess it
kind of depends on what your criteria
are you know one of my favorite quotes
about deployment and I'm drawing a blank
on who I think it's a karo bomb or I
can't remember the fellows name but
basically he said that you know
continuous deployment doesn't mean that
you always deploy every release it means
that you've proven that it can be
deployed out there certainly there are
there are things like kubernetes and
stuff now that do the clustering
technology and in rolling out versions
and things that make it easier to roll
back so if you have a plug-in or
something with that you could probably
make it you could make it work but I
think you know one of the ideas is if
you're using deployment schemes like
Bluegreen deployment those kinds of
things it's probably going to be more of
a manual flip the switch and decide
which one is it really good enough is it
ready or not if you're just rolling it
out there just to make it available
without putting it into production then
certainly you can do that there's no
reason again you couldn't drive it with
Jenkins to automatically deploy it out
there and certainly some companies do
that they always just get the latest and
just assume it but you might also want
to have a human kind of gating that
decision as well this is really a
Jenkins point but I'm aware they're
organizations that are doing hundreds
thousands of deploys per day at that
scale you'd probably want a computer
making a lot of the decisions and not
having a person have to do all that
absolutely if you're one of those
organizations where you are just always
putting out the latest and certainly you
could want to automate that and that
would certainly be something you could
drive through Jenkins want to spend a
little time on the implementation of
Jenkins itself
language is it implemented in I don't
honestly know I think it is probably
Java but I'm not I'm not entirely sure
is it
open-source there is an open-source
version of it certainly there's also an
Enterprise version of it but it is that
there is open-source as well does it
have a corporate sponsor that
contributes most of the patches yeah
there's a company called cloud bees out
there and the the gentleman who
originally created Jenkins is the the
one of the heads of cloud bees out there
and they do do enterprise support for
Jenkins but the really nice thing about
the relationship with cloud bees is
they're they are part of the Jenkins
community they are a big part and the
vast majority of what they work on gets
contributed back to the open-source
version out there so it's not just like
a company doing things they are part of
the open-source community they're
engaged with other people out there
answering questions those kinds of
things and so yeah it's it's very it's a
cool sort of relationship in there in
that they are giving a lot back to that
while they're also supporting the
enterprise aspects of it move on now and
this will be our last main topic is
adoption suppose we're in an environment
which does not have a build server
meaning that all these tasks would be
done manually or maybe ad hoc or custom
tools where does the advocacy for
adopting jenkins usually come from you
know honestly I think it probably comes
organically through a lot of
organizations out there I typically have
seen these these sorts of things come
from a group who says we have to do
something we have to find a way to do
something better we have to be more
efficient in it we're spending too much
time on this and they start looking for
an answer out there and you know they
start looking probably at what what is
considered quote unquote industry
standard or what do a lot of people use
and so they'll get something and try it
and if they get it and try it then that
message gets communicated via word of
mouth or be experienced
to other groups out there you know
developers are very smart they're going
to find the the most the best way so
they can spend most their time coding
and not have to worry as much about this
sort of these pieces of it and that's
part two of what the DevOps movement is
- I think when you get operations people
working with development out there
they're both looking for the best
solution and something like Jenkins that
provides this kind of workflow
automation through it once people start
to see what it can do then they start to
think about other ideas and other
opportunities and things they can use it
for the other way I think it comes into
is as I said there's a huge ecosystem of
plugins out there and so pretty much any
of the major even open source
applications out there these days that
do tooling kinds of things will have a
plugin for Jenkins so a lot of time you
start looking at the tool like git or
something and you see oh there's a
plugin for Jenkins and wow that would be
cool if I could have my builds
automatically kicked off or have Jenkins
detect changes in my source control and
kick off the bills out there so I think
all those factors kind of play into it
so it's more of a of a breath sort of a
bottom-up kind of advocacy that happens
maybe then more of a top down some
DevOps tools and and I'm not sure
whether it's fair to group Jenkins as a
DevOps tool but they are specialized
enough that you mostly find skills for
writing for example puppet or chef
scripts in the DevOps team versus other
skills like shell scripting that you'd
expect everyone could do as needed or
the Jenkins files would you typically
have a DevOps
or a build and release engineer who's
mastered the Jenkins file language or is
it something really everyone's going to
be expected to write their own Jenkins
files for their modules you know I think
it's probably going a variable
organization but first thing I would say
is that DevOps our Jenkins is very much
a DevOps tool they're they're
conferences and stuff now are kind of
geared towards that whole DevOps model
and I think it does provide that sort of
the DevOps functionality some of that
that's been missing for a while
but I have seen in even in where I work
and stuff that developers you know have
been willing to jump in and write
jinkins jobs and work with that it the
nice thing is like I said if you're if
you're a programmer writing your
pipeline is code programming your
pipeline probably feels pretty natural
to you being able to use constructs in
there and steps and write code and test
it and run at those sorts of things
probably feels more natural to you now
then perhaps filling in the web forms
did before out there so I think that the
pipeline says code has opened up perhaps
more doors to using Jenkins and at
access there but I think it's it's been
what I've seen is that it's really not
been the case that people are really
hesitant to use it or kind of put it off
to other people now you may have a group
of course at once to have standard ways
of doing things creating what we call
share pipeline libraries and stuff
standard ways of doing things out there
but I think it's it's a it's a very low
cost of entry for anybody who wants to
work with it I could see this spanning
across concerns of many different groups
because the developer generally knows
how to compile or build and package
their application but the DevOps would
have a better idea of how do we get this
pushed out on to the production network
which machines does this piece of code
need to run on so it's kind of a
cross-cutting thing yeah absolutely you
know and there are certainly other tools
out there like Gradle the Gradle build
system which can run test cases and
those sorts of things you can define
targets or tasks they call them in
Gradle to those kinds of things and
invoke those from Jenkins so you can
actually have your testers writing tests
you know when people writing deployment
scripts and stuff and then Jenkins again
just becomes kind of the orchestrator at
the overall at the higher level so as
long as you can say this is how you
invoke my part of the process then you
can translate that into a Jenkins
pipeline easily we've covered pretty
much everything I wanted to about
Jenkins is there anything you wanted to
mention or want us to cover that we
haven't hit on I guess I would just
maybe just really quickly mention that
they there is a new graphical interface
they're working on called blue ocean out
there in that it's still a little bit
rough in some spots
out there but I think in the future it's
going to provide a nice sort of
graphical interface for people who
aren't as comfortable diving into
writing pipelines as code being able to
look at that there's also the concept of
shared pipeline libraries I've touched
on just briefly but the idea of being
able to take your code and kind of put
things in there that you want to share
across groups it's basically a source
management repository with a certain
structure you put your code in there and
then there are ways to bring it in to
the Jenkins pipeline as well out there
and use that so that's that that's a
very nice thing to have out there and I
would just say I think that it's really
worthwhile for anybody who's looking to
do continuous delivery and I don't I
don't work for cloud B's I'm not you
know any getting anything from this but
I just wanted I'd say from my experience
Jenkins is a very easy-to-use tool it
does seem to have a lot of flexibility
now and I really feel like with the
whole DevOps movement in here it
provides a lot of opportunities for for
groups to migrate towards that I'm glad
you brought up the point about shared
libraries that was something I had
wanted to ask you about what I've seen
in Jenkins one is absolutely no
modularity so tons of copy and pasted
jobs and you'll see job XYZ job XYZ -
one job XYZ - - somebody wanted to run
it slightly differently the idea that
the Jenkins jobs are now going to be
code is great because now we think more
like programmers so of course the first
thing I want to do is if programmers can
I create a module or a function or
something I can call from different
places and have it run the same way so
I'm not copying and pasting it sounds
like they've solved that problem or
going in that direction yeah I think
that you know the shared pipeline lie
berries are a nice way to do that of
course I mean if you you know sometimes
you can parameterize things and that
sort of thing but if you want to just
have common code there is a shared
pipeline library structure out there
there's there's essentially three parts
of it very quickly there is a resources
area so basically you're just defining a
structure and your resources is one is
for like data files out there JSON files
any kind of data files you want and then
there is a source area SRC which is more
like the kind of Java source path out
there that cut that gets added to your
class path automatically when you're
using that and then there's one called
bars out there for these global
variables and that can be pretty much
any code and like defined in a groovy
script or groovy file with an object and
methods and such on it and the FAR's is
probably the easiest to use but yes you
can take that create that structure put
it up in a source management repository
configure and Jenkins say Jenkins this
is where my shared pipeline library is
I'm going to call it food I want you to
get it out of this branch use this
version and then once you've defined it
globally in Jenkins your script can
bring it in there's a couple of
different ways there's a an annotation
at library annotation you can bring it
in and then in declarative there's
another way to bring it in as well but
you can bring that in and that the cool
thing about that as well I mentioned the
declarative and the scripted syntax and
I said there were some things you could
do in the scripted syntax with like
loops and variables that you couldn't do
in declarative you can always create
your pipeline library as scripted syntax
and still load it in and declarative and
get that functionality she can get kind
of the hybrid approach the best of the
best of both worlds out there often the
case with declarative programming 5% of
the time you just have to write a little
bit of imperative code yes absolutely
and that's that there are a couple ways
to work around that there actually is
also a script block that you can put in
your declarative to actually use some
localized scripted syntax but the
pipeline libraries are probably your
best bet in that case let's move on to
rap
the show for our listeners you'd like to
find your book where can they obtain it
probably the easiest way is is a good ol
Amazon out there if you go out there
Jenkins - up and running you should find
it out there they've been kind of
running low on copies lately but they're
got under stand they're getting some
more in out there so just checkout you
can search by my name or Jenkins - out
there on Amazon any listeners would like
to contact you or follow you where can
they find you I am at at Brent C Laster
on Twitter BRE and T C L ast er is the
last name also on LinkedIn under Brent
Laster out there so yeah feel free to
reach out to me always happy to talk to
people about topics like Jenkins are
good or continuous delivery Brent thank
you very much for speaking to software
engineering radio thanks Robert I've
enjoyed it appreciate you having me on
the show for software engineering radio
this has been Robert blumen thanks for
listening the SC radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website @ SC - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the web site that will reach us on
LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through our
slack channel at SC radio.com you can
also email us at team @ SC - radio net
this and all other episodes of se Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening